<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-31T11:18:54-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Saoud Khalifah’s Blog</title><subtitle>Saoud Khalifah's personal blog on experiences as an engineer and CEO at Fakespot. Join to read the latest on our fight against fraud and untrustworthy content on the Internet.</subtitle><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><entry><title type="html">Amazon Fake Review Data Breach</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/amazon-fake-review-data-breach" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon Fake Review Data Breach" /><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/the-amazon-fake-review-data-breach</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/amazon-fake-review-data-breach">&lt;p&gt;The recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safetydetectives.com/blog/amazon-reviews-leak-report/&quot;&gt;data leak report&lt;/a&gt; exposing millions of records incriminating professional reviewers and sellers engaging in fake review fraud did not surprise us at all at Fakespot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen Facebook groups, WhatsApp groups, WeChat and many other social platforms hosting the meeting grounds for unscrupulous sellers/agencies/brands to get in touch with folks that would write reviews for their products, obviously in exchange for compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first detected the first signs of these types of promotional reviews in the tail end of 2015 and they exploded in volume by 2016 and 2017. The incentivized reviews had disclaimers that mentioned the review authors received products for free/compensation in exchange for writing the review. The amount of these types of compensated reviews reached epidemic levels and Amazon had to react. Amazon officially banned any reviews with text mentioning that kind of disclaimer in the late months of 2016 by doing specific keyword scanning within submitted reviews. The ripple effect of this ban is clearly seen today with social media platforms ending up hosting the subterfuge of Amazon sellers to obtain fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/compensated_review.png&quot; alt=&quot;An example of a compensated review from 2017 for a book&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of a compensated review from 2017 for a book&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the companies in the data leak was a relatively well known brand that is a competitor to Anker, RAVPower and other brands in the electronic accessories space, a hotbed of fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular brand named Aukey was implicated in the data leak and had hundreds of listings taken down by Amazon. As of today, there were 292 listings on Amazon down 77% from 1,236 listings that Fakespot has analyzed with over close to half a million reviews &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com/company/aukey&quot;&gt;(https://www.fakespot.com/company/aukey)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/auk.png&quot; alt=&quot;AUKEY Fakespot Company Page Screenshot&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;AUKEY Fakespot Company Page Screenshot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the average Fakespot grade and adjusted rating for the company’s products, the results aren’t flattering. We can say that it wasn’t a shock to see this brand (and others) be included in the data dump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subset  of Fakespot’s models have been trained specifically to pick up on signals that reviews and reviewers can be sourced via these promotional review campaigns. We believe these types of reviews are the more insidious fake reviews as they are mostly written by humans that have an intrinsic bias embedded. Fakespot’s engines look for a targeted amount of historic and present parameters to determine if the reviews belong to such a category and are pointed out to our users via our Fakespot grade or our reports with the deception level metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will this data leak change anything for the current trend of fake reviews on Amazon?&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t think so. A lot of the banned sellers will be reinstated and probably a good amount of the reviews will be part of the Amazon “purges” (read my &lt;a href=&quot;https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; to understand these events) but it is a slap on the wrist and the fake review economy continues full steam ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what happens when you have millions of 3rd party sellers running amok on the Amazon platform and so much profit to be gained by duping unsuspecting consumers with these types of reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot today and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real or not, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">The recent data leak report exposing millions of records incriminating professional reviewers and sellers engaging in fake review fraud did not surprise us at all at Fakespot.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is buying your influence in 2021?</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is buying your influence in 2021?" /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What can money buy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on who you are asking, the answers vary:&lt;br /&gt;
Power, comfort, land .. maybe even a sprinkle of Fake News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How about your influence? Is that for sale?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the explosive rise of TikTok, it was only a matter of time until we started seeing videos such as the ones in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2020/12/15/22174581/walmart-amazon-tiktok-employee-worker-influencer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;this article by Vox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employees in the monster factory warehouses of Amazon are now using the social platform as a medium to showcase the dark side of getting your shipment in 2 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of constant surveillance, optimized algorithmic performance evaluations, and being a human robot are hallmarks of the job. More and more videos trickle onto social media uncovering the reality of modern commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the table, this must look like an onslaught of nightmare PR and press. How do you fight this fire that only seems to be growing and growing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would depend on the size of your treasury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a treasury the size of several countries cumulative GDP, you might as well fight fire with fire, change peoples’ perceptions and distort reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Vine&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pay to get 5 star reviews with Amazon Vine program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/amazon-influencer-how-to-make-money-2019-2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Influencer program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/whats-an-amazon-fc-ambassador-and-are-they-okay-1837274685&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Influencer army&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/news/tiktok-sale-deadline-elapses-as-negotiations-with-us-continue/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart is seeking to increase their stake in TikTok&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An army of influencers fighting under the banner of the wronged and the oppressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait.. which side is the wronged one again? The Influencer Amnesia has struck, yet again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a feedback loop running right in-front of us. The influencers posting rave tweets and posts are also the ones that are buying fake followers, upvotes and many more. The savage cycle only repeats itself and proliferates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like the industry is too far gone to revert. What is even more astounding is that buying influencers doesn’t just limit itself to PR and media. Every facet of the Internet is affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influencers aren’t only working to improve companies’ reputations by tweeting or using TikTok. By now, it should come as no surprise that &lt;a href=&quot;https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;more than 40%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (!) of the reviews you’re reading may have been manipulated and are unreliable. These types of campaigns are only growing with more reviews being written with the only intent to influence you and your buying decision. Without you even knowing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot today and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real or not, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">What can money buy?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Let’s talk about fake reviews - part 1</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let's talk about fake reviews - part 1" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1">&lt;p&gt;Fake reviews garner much attention and controversy worldwide. It is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; primary reason Fakespot was created. Fakespot was launched after I was scammed on Amazon with a product that had hundreds of fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading the reviews for this product, it was obvious that the seller had implanted fake reviews with the use of bots, spiced up with some human input. The product was freshly launched and it had &lt;em&gt;hundreds of 5 star reviews&lt;/em&gt; in a matter of hours for a completely no name brand!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already familiar with black hat techniques fraudsters use to increase their listings’ rankings due to my security background, a passion I developed in my early teenage years. In case you were wondering… Yes, I was a hacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the age of 18, I submitted my first bug bounties to the Zero Day Initiative, a pioneer of the bug bounty programs when there were none. The first vulnerability I discovered was a &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft PowerPoint&lt;/strong&gt; buffer overflow. My research later lead me to finding bugs in software ranging from &lt;strong&gt;Adobe PDF Reader&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;WinAmp&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Foxit&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;VLC Player&lt;/strong&gt; to some more &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;check out my publicly published vulnerabilities/exploits &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exploit-db.com/search?e_author=skd&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re curious&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/metasploit_pp_exploit.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Metasploit module for the PowerPoint vulnerability I found way back in the day.&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Metasploit module for the PowerPoint vulnerability I found way back in the day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funny story: I applied for a Microsoft internship at the time I received the payout for the bug bounty. Back in those days, Microsoft was notorious for “hating” on anyone who would find weaknesses in their products especially security researchers. Needless to say, they immediately rejected my application. It just shows how much Microsoft has changed since then.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My love for security has taught me that, reverse engineering to the lowest level is always critical. Especially, if you want to understand the fundamentals and scope to the problem you are encountering. That mindset helped me discover a completely different class of vulnerabilities altogether, the social context vulnerabilities in eCommerce: &lt;strong&gt;fake reviews&lt;/strong&gt; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot was initially built to automate the process of analyzing the trustworthiness of reviews. After all, who has hours of free time to dissect and verify the reviews they’re reading? Since the launch of Fakespot in 2015, the state of fake reviews and eCommerce fraud has emerged and evolved in ways that I wouldn’t have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving in to fake reviews and eCommerce fraud, let’s talk about eCommerce and take a look at the total volume and growth of sales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shopify_sales_graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;eCommerce past years growth and forecast for 2021 - Source: Shopify&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;eCommerce past years growth and forecast for 2021 - Source: Shopify&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;eCommerce sales are forecast to be close to &lt;em&gt;$4 trillion dollars&lt;/em&gt; this year. That is &lt;em&gt;nearly 20%&lt;/em&gt; of the GDP for the United States in 2019 alone. These numbers are astonishing and showcase the vast opportunities in eCommerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more sales happen online in the year of 2020. We can only see eCommerce gobbling up even more sales from brick and mortal retail as consumers work from home in quarantine. This is indeed the era of the &lt;em&gt;digital gold rush&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Make no mistake, it also the era of the digital Wild West.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/wild_west_meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;That's the truth, Clint.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;That’s the truth, Clint.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive into trends we see with fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot has analyzed over &lt;strong&gt;8 billion reviews&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;1 billion reviewers&lt;/strong&gt; and served over &lt;strong&gt;20 million users&lt;/strong&gt; visiting &lt;strong&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/strong&gt;. From our analysis, we can clearly understand the trends that show the increase in fraud over the last 3 years with each month in comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/fakespot_avg_graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;The monthly average of analyses that had &amp;gt;= 30% unreliable reviews - Source: Fakespot&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The monthly average of analyses that had &amp;gt;= 30% unreliable reviews - Source: Fakespot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data unveils the whole story for the trend of fake reviews. We have comparable rises each year in the amount of unreliable reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the averages from March 2020 to August 2020 reached &lt;strong&gt;record numbers never seen before&lt;/strong&gt;. This sequence of increases would only occur in Black Friday and Christmas shopping seasons of prior years. Sellers are quoted as saying “It was Black Friday everyday” &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/article/people-shopping-more-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and we all experienced the widespread stock depletion on Amazon and other platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also take note that in September 2020 Amazon significantly &lt;strong&gt;purged&lt;/strong&gt;, albeit in a delayed fashion, a large chunk of fake reviews to move it down from the &lt;strong&gt;43.75%&lt;/strong&gt; average we see in August. Likely, in preparation for Prime Day and the impending holiday shopping season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is quite different, &lt;em&gt;to say the least&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the majority of the world went into lockdown the importance of reviews increases for sellers and consumers alike. We shop online, unable to judge the product by touching, feeling and physically testing it. Thus, we heavily rely on the opinions of others that have purchased the product. &lt;strong&gt;I believe one of the great innovations of the Internet is shared knowledge, and reviews are a conduit of that.&lt;/strong&gt; Unfortunately, sellers also know that reviews can make or break their sales and they are abusing that to the maximum for their advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This overview of the general trends is useful in understanding the scale of eCommerce fraud. Fake reviews and the fraud surrounding eCommerce is extensive, complex and deep. To go through all the topics requires a sequence of posts with this being the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to try out Fakespot and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Fake reviews garner much attention and controversy worldwide. It is the primary reason Fakespot was created. Fakespot was launched after I was scammed on Amazon with a product that had hundreds of fake reviews. When reading the reviews for this product, it was obvious that the seller had implanted fake reviews with the use of bots, spiced up with some human input. The product was freshly launched and it had hundreds of 5 star reviews in a matter of hours for a completely no name brand!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fakespot Highlights - AI powered summaries</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fakespot Highlights - AI powered summaries" /><published>2020-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries">&lt;p&gt;Super excited to announce that we’ve just released, &lt;strong&gt;Fakespot Highlights&lt;/strong&gt;, a powerful AI generated addition to our analysis reports on Fakespot.com that consists of direct summaries of reviews that you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to know about before purchasing a product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/fakespot_highlights.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Fakespot Highlights&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot Highlights will organize relevant information into 5 categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;What is the product’s quality and characteristics?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packaging/appearance&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How is the product’s packaging and physical attributes?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitiveness&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How does the product stack up to the competition?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shipping&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;What was the general experience with the product’s shipping?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How was/is the price?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights will also further categorize the details by sentiment with Positive, Neutral and Negative sentiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new feature is powered by multiple machine learned models, both supervised and unsupervised, built by our talented data science team. The models were trained on over 7 billion+ reviews using our proprietary in-house stack that delivers blazing fast results in an eCommerce setting. That means no 3rd party APIs and no reliance on outside solutions (always awesome in my book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try Fakespot Highlights, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;. After installing the extension, browse to a product page on Amazon.com and click to Analyze or Reanalyze. I would also recommend analyzing a product you’ve owned for a while and see if the Highlights match your personal experience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are always excited to build products and features that help our users in getting the best eCommerce experience. This feature is currently in Beta but we are constantly improving the technology in an evolutionary manner. If you have any suggestions, do not hesitate to get in &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:saoud@fakespot.com&quot;&gt;touch with me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Super excited to announce that we’ve just released, Fakespot Highlights, a powerful AI generated addition to our analysis reports on Fakespot.com that consists of direct summaries of reviews that you have to know about before purchasing a product.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fakespot now supports eBay</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/08/03/fakespot-now-supports-ebay-detect-fake-ebay-sellers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fakespot now supports eBay" /><published>2020-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/08/03/fakespot-guardian-now-supports-ebay</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/08/03/fakespot-now-supports-ebay-detect-fake-ebay-sellers">&lt;p&gt;I am excited to announce that our Fakespot Chrome extension is now able to detect fraudulent, bot, fake and counterfeit sellers on all the English based eBay websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be able to determine the authenticity of a seller by using Fakespot Guard that will display a badge on the eBay listing page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fakespot Guard badge will let you know if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A seller has sold counterfeits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A seller has committed shipping fraud by not shipping items or scamming users.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A seller account got hacked and is now listing fake listings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many more detection methods that utilize our powerful Fakespot artificial intelligence analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/guard_ebay.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Fakespot Chrome Extension in action on eBay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fakespot engines have been detecting eCommerce fraud for close to 5 years now on Amazon, Sephora, BestBuy, Steam and Walmart. We now bring the Fakespot experience to the largest eCommerce auction site in the world with eBay. Our user’s safety and trustworthiness experience in browsing these sites is paramount and we will continuously develop products that &lt;em&gt;bring back trust and transparency to the Internet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; today for free and protect yourself from eCommerce scams.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">I am excited to announce that our Fakespot Chrome extension is now able to detect fraudulent, bot, fake and counterfeit sellers on all the English based eBay websites.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing - Fakespot Guardian</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/06/15/introducing-fakespot-guardian" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing - Fakespot Guardian" /><published>2020-06-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/06/15/introducing-fakespot-guardian</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/06/15/introducing-fakespot-guardian">&lt;p&gt;Fakespot is always exploring new ways to protect consumers from fraud using our proprietary technology that we have developed over the last couple of years. Our mission has never changed: use state of the art technology to protect our users and &lt;em&gt;bring back trust and transparency&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am proud to announce our latest evolution in detecting eCommerce fraud, &lt;strong&gt;Fakespot Guardian&lt;/strong&gt;. With Guardian, we are now able to detect bad sellers and defend consumers from the issues that are plaguing eCommerce today. Guard is available first on our popular Chrome extension and will be later expanded across the Fakespot platform. Combined with our Fake Review Analysis engines, Fakespot has taken another step in providing a service that ensures users get the best products from the best sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology that powers Guardian utilizes a lot of what we have learned and seen with the rise of eCommerce. Our detection methods are powered by the potent combination of machine learning and natural language processing (also powered by ML in certain segments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very excited to give our users the confidence they need to trust Amazon, which currently is becoming the largest 3rd party marketplace in the world. Many problems ranging from counterfeits, fake products, defective products and scams in general come with the rise of 3rd party marketplaces and Guardian is here to put that in check and provide the insight that is needed when we shop online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; to start using Fakespot Guardian today for free.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Fakespot is always exploring new ways to protect consumers from fraud using our proprietary technology that we have developed over the last couple of years. Our mission has never changed: use state of the art technology to protect our users and bring back trust and transparency.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/03/17/reflections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections" /><published>2020-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/03/17/reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/03/17/reflections">&lt;p&gt;Most of us wouldn’t have predicted that in 2020, in the year of the rat, the animal that brought the bubonic plague to medieval Europe hundreds of years ago, would start this way. A virus sweeping the world, the silent killer that causes market crashes, your favorite actor to test positive and an apocalypse looming over the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sea of darkness, it is hard to find the rays of light that bring positivity to our lives. It is in times like these, I believe that reflection is important. The best way to reflect on our current situation is to understand how our forefathers tackled such a dangerous problem and to put things in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meditations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a book I highly recommend to my family and friends whenever they face adversity in their lives. I first read it in my early twenties and it drastically changed my perspectives in life. It introduced me to the mind of the greatest philosopher warrior king, Marcus Aurelius, the emperor who faced an array of dangers in his leadership of the largest empire in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the dangers that he never mentions directly in his written thoughts but a danger he faced everyday was the Antonine plague. A pandemic so devastating that it nearly brought the world’s greatest empire to its knees and wiped out as much as one third of the population with a mortality rate of 25%. It caused shockwaves within the Roman culture and altered the way everyone lived their everyday lives for close to 15 years when the plague ran rampant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the biggest events that affected Marcus’s stewardship was when his co-emperor Lucius Verus, a sort of vice president, died of the plague. This shifted most of the power of the vast empire towards Marcus and only increased his ever-growing list of responsibilities. What is clear from Marcus’s actions and written accounts is that he held an unwavering spirit of duty and service for his people and his kingdom. He won various daunting military campaigns against the Sarmatians and Germanic tribes that resulted in the empire recovering its power and safety for its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is during these campaigns that the book Meditations was mostly written. It holds in its contents a true testament to a leader that faced mortal dangers. Both visible and invisible with no choice but to lead his tribe to the surface of light in the sea of darkness that enveloped them for nearly two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is inspirational to look back at what our ancestors faced and how they came out of it. We can only learn from their experiences in our times of difficulties, gaining resilience and perseverance within our own actions. No matter what we face, there have been periods in history that have been significantly worse and arguably more apocalyptic. I am grateful for that notion in my reflection today. I know that soon, &lt;strong&gt;this too shall pass&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Most of us wouldn’t have predicted that in 2020, in the year of the rat, the animal that brought the bubonic plague to medieval Europe hundreds of years ago, would start this way. A virus sweeping the world, the silent killer that causes market crashes, your favorite actor to test positive and an apocalypse looming over the horizon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Biased, by design</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/25/biased-by-design" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biased, by design" /><published>2019-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/25/biased-by-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/25/biased-by-design">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artificial intelligence has resulted in a revolution of thought. Its immense innovation brings about self-reflection on our own imperfections as humans and the inversion, the transcendent perfection that a computer can bring from the uncharted territories of simulating the human brain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all, the decisions we make in life have the essence of bias attached to them. Think about the last minuscule decision you’ve made. Your lunch meal, song selection or the latest leased car. These decisions are colored by our own personal bias in the thought process. From a very early age, we have been influenced by actors that surround us with their own biases. Whenever we conduct the next decision, it is conjoined with our experiences that dictate our determinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As civilization evolved, the bedrock of developed societies demanded entities that would hold minimal inherent biases. The recognizable example, courts and the justice system. One of the earliest codes of law, the Babylonian Code of Hammurabi (c. 1754 BC), consisted of 282 laws ranging from contract litigation, inheritance and more. One of these  codes mention the consequences of a decision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(Code 5) If a judge has given a verdict, rendered a decision, granted a written judgment, and afterward has altered his judgment, that judge shall be prosecuted for altering the judgment he gave and shall pay twelvefold the penalty laid down in that judgment. Further, he shall be publicly expelled from his judgment-seat and shall not return nor take his seat with the judges at a trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a rational and necessary law code as constant changes in judgments would decimate the thoughts of a stable and efficient authoritative system. However, the consequences and pressures applied by such a code are immeasurable. To appease our own notion that humans can be unbiased, we appoint judges and panels of fellow juries to adjudicate other humans on matters of high importance. This is the best system we have come up with. Unfortunately there is one intrinsic human problem: we are biased, as we are, by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, those systems are flawed. Imperfection is what leads us astray. However, you might argue that this trait has allowed us to conquer new territories, venture into the unknown, survive under the most strenuous circumstances and even further advance civilizations’ developments. The survival and evolution of mankind is dependent on the trait and if you examine any conflict between humans, you will come to agree that it will always be a result of an aggregate storm of biases. Let’s go back in time to the dawn of the scientific revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the mid-1600s and a fortuitous event occurred. Under the shade of a genus Malus tree, an apple fell and an observant scientist presented a theory. These were the thoughts that sparked the theory of gravitation as described by Isaac Newton, resulting in a momentous event of enlightenment for humanity and science. A thesis came into shape about a force that everyone was aware of physically and at the least, subconsciously, but no one’s ever decided to describe it scientifically until Newton. You could argue that the discovery of gravity was on par with the discovery of the definition of the number zero, a concept early humans could not wrap their minds around but the integer revolutionized mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bias needs the same enlightenment event to occur&lt;/strong&gt;. In an age where artificial intelligence and data are already conducting decisions for our lives and livelihoods: loans/mortgages, job applications, autopilots, your next movie recommendations and many more facets of life, all controlled by software today. Computers are dictated by algorithms all the way down to the inner core, the chips that control the hardware. Some of these incredibly low-level algorithms already have weaknesses that in certain cases result in security vulnerabilities (ex: Spectre/Meltdown, targets caching algorithms in CPU chips) and plethora of other issues. Most of them, also, have the authors’ and companies’ biases embedded. As we move up the stack from the chip, to the different layers of software, that is where we see a familiar concept unravel; an aggregate of biases that only compounds and propagates with each layer. Does the company have a mandate to cut cost? The Boeing 737 Max software is a morbid example. Do you prefer to use the English unit system? Due to a failure to convert English to metric system, the $327.6 million Mars Climate Orbiter mission ended being incinerated in the atmosphere of Mars. Imperfections abound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers epitomize perfection. They live by the laws of binary, and in the future, will prosper in the certain/uncertain quantum universe. As artificial intelligence reaches the levels of sci-fi utopian dreams, we will have entities that combine perfection with the dawn of &lt;em&gt;unbiased thoughts&lt;/em&gt;. Can you imagine a future where your fellow human would be judged by an AI powered judge? Does that solve any kind of problem for society? Or is imperfection a quality that is required for human survival and redemption? We will find out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Artificial intelligence has resulted in a revolution of thought. Its immense innovation brings about self-reflection on our own imperfections as humans and the inversion, the transcendent perfection that a computer can bring from the uncharted territories of simulating the human brain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">De chao, ordo</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/04/de-chao-ordo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De chao, ordo" /><published>2019-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/04/de-chao-ordo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2019/08/04/de-chao-ordo">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We’ve been bestowed with a consciousness to interpret reality, we’ve been bestowed with the order of things that surrounds us at every moment. However, the origins of the universe were and still are engorged in mists of chaos. Out of that chaos, order came to be, at least on our planet. How is that possible? Was it by chance? Was it the divine element that stirred the pot and nudged it the “right” way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grand pictures aside, I’ve been a software engineer for most of my life starting off with programming at a young age. Back then it was more about having fun without pressure, coding DbZ games on the fly in Visual Basic 6.0 and inadvertently learning a skill that would set the stage for the rest of my life. As my craft for the creation of software blossomed and matured, I became accustomed to the notion that every serious and professional endeavor in life is surrounded by principles. Principles that spawn order. A set of rules that come from years of understanding and experience. Escaping chaos’ grasp, you are now able to forge and create. In the case of software (and &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; else as we’ll see later), an intangible program that is able to do any number of things that you’d put your mind towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software design principles aren’t unlike the architectural principles of physical structures. A great professor of mine assigned us a book for a whole semester of learning for the fundamentals of software design. However, this was not your typical software design book. The book was Vitruvius’s “&lt;em&gt;De architectura&lt;/em&gt;”, a collection of ten books written under the patronage of emperor Augustus. Within the series of texts, it is glaring to see the sophistication of ancient Roman engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pantheon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Pantheon, commissioned by Agrippa and then finished by Hadrian (120s AD), still stands today with a ~4500 ton Concrete dome held by eight barrel vaults resulting in the largest free standing unreinforced dome in the world.&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 50%; height: 150px;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/oculus-pantheon2.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Pantheon, commissioned by Agrippa and then finished by Hadrian (120s AD), still stands today with a ~4500 ton Concrete dome held by eight barrel vaults resulting in the largest free standing unreinforced dome in the world.&quot; style=&quot;height: 150px;; max-width: 50%; margin-left: 5px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 16px; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;The Pantheon, commissioned by Agrippa and then finished by Hadrian (120s AD), still stands today with a ~4500 ton Concrete dome held by eight barrel vaults resulting in the largest free standing unreinforced dome in the world.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the development of strong, stable buildings, isn’t so different from the development of strong, stable software. If you want a building to last the tests of time, it requires the same set of strengths starting from the foundational principles. A vision and a blueprint that encompasses the requirements set by the engineers, the creator and the beneficiaries. What are the chaotic elements that a building would encounter? Wind, rain, fire, the natural elements that ravage at its core and human sourced elements, like war. It’s clear to see, Romans were passionate and discipline-crazed about their crafts when they built  structures of an ethereal quality that would last an eternity, at least in their eyes. With that in the back of our minds, let’s fast-forward a couple of years into my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a website that would analyze and detect fake reviews. It started off as a side project that was used by family and friends but grew into a service that is used by millions of users. Scalability of the service was one of the first chaotic elements encountered as my blueprint for the project did not account for the fact that other people beside myself and my family would want to use it. The beauty of software in comparison to buildings; it’s never too late to go back and refactor aspects of the application to suit the new requirement. My principles of software engineering have constantly evolved as the project grew however, I’ve always had consistent goal of maintaining quality through taking a step back to view everything from the highest level and observe where the project was heading and the challenges that may be encountered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently in the 4th year of building a company that has a critical mission of bringing trustworthiness back to the Internet. An immense journey riddled with numerous ups and downs where I’ve been the most astute student of Fate. The core values of the company were set from the inception in detecting deception and that is something that has never changed. Forging business relationships and electrifying team spirit have all been skills that I had to evolve and learn consistently as the team grew. An interesting fact that I have observed through the experience with Fakespot is that fake reviews at face value are the epitome of chaotic elements that are human sourced, made to manipulate other unsuspecting consumers. Continuously, fighting chaos intertwined with the start-up life, sometimes feels like a fireman putting out fires on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one common theme that my career and personal life have shown me. Diminishing chaotic elements in the balance of scales is something that is crucial in not just engineering, architecture, business ventures but every other aspect of life. That is something that we, as human beings with higher levels of consciousness with the ability to monitor and detect chaos, must strive for. Moving the scales towards order in building a company, software, relationships, family and most importantly your own mental state is something we should all devote ourselves toward. As we age, we hopefully improve our skill to realize and detect chaotic elements that fall into our lives. It is up to us, to rip or diminish these elements for the better well-being and stronger foundation that we all  want to seek.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">We’ve been bestowed with a consciousness to interpret reality, we’ve been bestowed with the order of things that surrounds us at every moment. However, the origins of the universe were and still are engorged in mists of chaos. Out of that chaos, order came to be, at least on our planet. How is that possible? Was it by chance? Was it the divine element that stirred the pot and nudged it the “right” way?</summary></entry></feed>