<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-29T15:59:22-05:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Saoud Khalifah’s Blog</title><subtitle>Saoud Khalifah's personal blog on experiences as an engineer and CEO at Fakespot. Join to read the latest on our fight against fraud and untrustworthy content on the Internet.</subtitle><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><entry><title type="html">Favorite Books of 2021</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/29/favorite-books-of-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Favorite Books of 2021" /><published>2021-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/29/favorite-books-of-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/29/favorite-books-of-2021">&lt;p&gt;Below I dive into books that I read/listened to this year that changed my perspectives and understandings in a variety of topics. Each entry will be accompanied by a brief summary of the book and notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books (in no particular order):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What You Do Is Who You Are: How to Create Your Business Culture by Ben Horowitz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/wyd.png&quot; alt=&quot;What You Do Is Who You Are: How to Create Your Business Culture&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly relevant book to me as it addresses the culture that you embed within the company you are building. This book by Ben Horowitz, who is a legend in this industry, enumerates characteristics of different cultures via stories from personal experience or history. There are many learning lessons in this book and it is targeting specifically the building blocks of a sustainable and enduring company culture, one of the cornerstones of a successful business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japanese culture has an unscrupulous attention to detail due to the awareness of mortality. This reminded me of Steve Job’s mantra (who self-admittedly was heavily inspired by Bushido) in waking up everyday as if thinking it is your last day. That’s how you produce your best work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your personal virtues are what what the culture will ultimately end up valuing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meaningful relationships between team members and team leads is how loyalty is formed. A nice example from Stripe is included in the book.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ben’s experience at Opsware: pivoting the whole company required a lot of maneuvering and leadership jiu jitsu that rested on the cultural values he evoked.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interesting take on wartime CEOs like Larry Page, Steve Jobs versus peacetime CEOs ala Tim Cook, Dara Khosrowshahi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Disagree but commit” in the old days of Netscape resulted in the imperfect (but usable and much needed) Javascript and other tech the Internet is built on today. Nothing built will be perfect and it is more important to start building rather than endlessly debating.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very interesting example involving Genghis Khan and his straying away from the status quo due to diversity and inclusiveness that was anathema to the rule of the day. Valued meritocracy versus aristocracy because of his own upbringing and personal experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coaching, and not management, was crucial for Fairchild Semiconductor. It can be argued it was the progenitor to the general SV culture today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. History Of The Peloponnesian War by Thucydides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/hist.png&quot; alt=&quot;History Of The Peloponnesian War&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have read this book previously in excerpts during high school (as some of you probably have) but never gave it a thorough examination from start to finish that it deserved. It’s a good thing I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has been quoted by Winston Churchill and many other preeminent leaders of our times due to its highly influential portrayal of human ideology, desire and spirit. The key lesson here is: Humans and their behaviors have remained unchanged even over 2,400 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pericles’ Funeral Oration was beautiful. I was quite surprised by how Pericles could simulate other peoples behaviors and interpretations of statements he was making so as to prevent any consequential actions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pericles headed the radical democracy that powered Athens in the early years of the Peloponnesian War. Unfortunately, when he passed and without his leadership, everything started to deteriorate. Was that a true democracy then if it rested on the shoulders of one individual?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impossibilities that are probable are more useful than possibilities that are improbable - Aristotle (from Poetics)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes death is not the ultimate deterrent because poverty drives necessity of action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desire and hope, one leads and one wants.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The descriptions of plague and massacres are horrific and are almost parallel to recent events in human history. One particular example of the massacre of a school at Mykalessos by barbaric Thracian mercenaries show cased how humanity can evaporate in an instant.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intense rivalry between Cleon and Nicias. One a war mongerer and the other a self-interested peace keeper (Nicias owned vast tracts of land).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conclusion: The true enemy of Athens was Athens itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Being You by Anil Seth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/being.png&quot; alt=&quot;Being You&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness has always been a topic that intrigued me. Especially after years of developing artificial intelligence systems, I have always wondered what kind of a task it would be to emulate or even create consciousness with AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book unpacks a lot of material from the neuroscience world introducing readers to concepts that may or may not have been evident before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A very interesting use of the Lempel-Ziv-Welch (LZW) lossless data compression algorithm to calculate the randomness and entropy rate of electrophysiological brain data. Using LZW, an algorithm that is used for example in .gif files, is such an intriguing concept. It makes sense that the higher the randomness of data, the harder it will be to compress and the less random the data, the higher the compression rate. This results in a measure of algorithmic complexity of our brains (wow!). Super interesting stuff and the utility of an algorithm that is from a completely different domain with completely different target use cases was mind-blowing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Order = integration, disorder = information in the sense of neuroscience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated information theory basically posits that the system or the whole (integration) is greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Panpsychism theory brings forth the idea that even atoms experience consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being alive != conscious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is consciousness stemmed from information from our senses combined with memories, reflexes and learnings resulting in the final integration in the form of consciousness?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interesting take on Bayesian inference and the feedback loop of: a priori -&amp;gt; likelihoods -&amp;gt; a posteriori. Reliability of information is critical here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humans are incredibly bad at measuring or judging time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teletrasportation paradox brings incredible ethical and legal questions that require a deep understanding of consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free energy principle posits that all life is “programmed” to reduce free energy and thus reduce entropy to get to an equilibrium state. It states that the brain is essentially an inference engine that tries to determine the states to do reduce free energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interesting use of allostasis in the sense of change of the body.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology is already working majorly on our consciousness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cerebral organoids look to be super interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The Order of Time by Carlo Rovelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/order.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Order of Time&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by the physicist Carlo Rovelli, this is a really fascinating take on explaining one of the hardest aspects of our reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of Horace verses at the start of every chapter is interesting, almost poignant, as there are interspersed hints that even our ancient forefathers were thinking deeply on the questions of time and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our language is inadequate in explaining hard concepts including time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time describes events, change and relations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interesting interpretation of time by Aristotle where a perspective of relativity is evident and the measure of change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time evolves from a world without time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The universe stats in a state of low entropy and change increases entropy, therefore in its inextricably linked with time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2nd law of thermodynamics is used to explain that entropy can never go below 0 and in a way imitates time as it goes in one direction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is entropy relative?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We get low entropy in form of photons from the Sun, close to the pure form of low entropy from the beginnings of the universe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The movement of particles results in heat and is ultimately the change we experience that then becomes an event&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our brains adapted to the concept of time using terms like past, present and future for survival but these terms do not make sense in the universe itself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Music can synchronize humans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The concept of durations is an artifact of the human brain even though there is no such thing as the present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. The Birth of Plenty: How the Prosperity of the Modern World Was Created by William J. Bernstein&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/birth.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Birth of Plenty: How the Prosperity of the Modern World Was Created&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book explains how we go to where we are today where entrepreneurs are able to create, innovate and generate value for modern societies. The book provides a great socioeconomic thesis of the times we live in and the developments from history that allowed us to get to this point by identifying 4 critical pillars: Property/Intellectual Rights, Scientific Method and Rationale, Free Flowing Capital Markets and Transportation/Communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a society lacks even one of these pillars or conditions, it will end up being less prosperous and inefficient with regards to economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Athens (and the communities surrounding it) evolved to become democracies due the society’s agrarian nature and roots. There needed to be a way in splitting up lots for farming and agriculture and as such democracy was formed to power such decisions by vote.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Along with democracy, Athens also had a concept of property rights intertwined within their governance. However, they lacked the 3 other pillars and therefore the polity was not effective and efficient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Macedon and Sparta were anti-democratic and oligarchic in nature due to their environments situated in valleys or coasts, resulting in slavery and no property rights except for the people in power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Dark Ages resulted in a completely collapse of all developments achieved by the ancients however was slowly rediscovered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magna Carta was the pivotal event for English common law in diluting the monarchy’s powers and spreading it to the barons and clergy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The freeing up of the resources and major religious movements such as the English Reformation lead to the Scientific Method championed by Francis Bacon and Isaac Newton.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With the Scientific Method, society moved away from Aristotelian Natural Philosophy, empirical testing now allowed for rapid advancement in science&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low interest rates allowed for capital to flow to inventors and to fund their experiments powered by the Scientific Method&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before free flowing capital markets, property rights and the scientific method, people had no incentive to pursue innovation due to the feudal system that basically provided no reward or protection for inventors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free capital flow of markets were achieved in the Netherlands and then imitated by Great Britain achieving the lowest interest rates in Europe. It isn’t a coincidence that both of these empires relied heavily on intercontinental maritime trade that reduced dependence on agriculture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High interest rates in other countries was due to the the seasonal aspects of harvests resulting in interest rates around or more than 30% (!) as loans were tied to crop outputs. Innovation cannot happen at these high level of interest rates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment banking and limited liability partnerships reduced liabilities for Dutch and British trade and was initiated by the need to mitigate and distribute risk among many investors versus only a couple, which could alleviate the disastrous effects for investors, in a time when vessels and ships would sink often.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transportation and communication effectiveness progressed rapidly after the Industrial revolution with the advent of the steam engine, telegraphs, cars. With an effective transportation and communication system, inventors can distribute their products effectively to customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final notes: If you are looking for a good read, you can’t go wrong with any of the books on this list. The pursuit of knowledge is what makes us truly exceptional.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Below I dive into books that I read/listened to this year that changed my perspectives and understandings in a variety of topics. Each entry will be accompanied by a brief summary of the book and notes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 million active installs!</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/20/one-million-installs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 million active installs!" /><published>2021-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/20/one-million-installs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/12/20/one-million-installs">&lt;p&gt;Super thrilled to announce that we have officially crossed 1 million active installs at Fakespot 🎉!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the installs milestone, 1.8 BILLION Fakespot Grades were displayed to our users in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mammoth achievement and that number will only grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/onebill.png&quot; alt=&quot;1.8 Billion Fakespot Grades Displayed in 2021&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are incredibly grateful to our loyal users that allow us to grow explosively and build technology that makes the world a better place, even, in the face of many challenges that we experienced this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look out for what we will announce in 2022 and beyond!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot for free today and stop wondering if those reviews are real or not. Download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/fakespot-fake-reviews-amazon/&quot;&gt;Firefox extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;Fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Super thrilled to announce that we have officially crossed 1 million active installs at Fakespot 🎉!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Truth Behind the Stars</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/08/24/the-truth-behind-the-stars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Truth Behind the Stars" /><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/08/24/the-truth-behind-the-stars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/08/24/the-truth-behind-the-stars">&lt;p&gt;There is one indisputable and ubiquitous feature of eCommerce platforms that powers a huge chunk of sales and conversions. That is the &lt;strong&gt;ratings (or reviews) system&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviews on the Internet had their major break back in 1995 when Amazon introduced, at that time, the groundbreaking method to share opinions online via the 5-star rating system.
However, this was not the first time a star rating system was used. For that, we need to go back to the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first printed evidence of a star rating system was in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%27s_Handbooks_for_Travellers&quot;&gt;Murray’s Handbooks for Travellers&lt;/a&gt;. These handbooks were travel guides that were published starting in &lt;strong&gt;1836&lt;/strong&gt;. It is interesting to see how human psychology renders a star rating system an easy way to digest opinions on a subject, a system that has been tried and proven over a span of hundreds of years. Human psychology remains consistent even when the medium of delivery has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary reasons behind reading a review are obvious: to understand a product and the service surrounding the transaction. We cannot test, touch, feel or view the product in physical form and, as such, we rely on the opinions of other customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diving deeper, reviews are critical in bringing confidence and trust for consumers when purchasing on marketplaces online. If a user views a review from a fellow customer, they are more than likely to have confidence to check out with the product as there is established validation. Cognitive biases are abound including a sprinkle of FOMO (&lt;em&gt;we’ll save that for a different post&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been numerous studies/surveys done on this topic. To summarize, the general average of consumers that read reviews before any kind of purchasing decision is high and hovers around the &lt;strong&gt;93% mark&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.qualtrics.com/blog/online-review-stats/&quot;&gt;(Qualtrics)&lt;/a&gt;. That is a significant percentage of users and, additionally, &lt;strong&gt;91% of 18-34 year olds trust reviews as much as a recommendation from a friend!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The influence of those orange stars is undeniable and we are increasingly dependent on them. Now, what if I told you those stars are flawed and can instead lead you to an unsatisfactory decision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s pull the curtain and take a peek behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Bayesian/Black-box ML Averaging of Ratings&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be shocked to find out that the average star rating that you see on platforms like Amazon and others is not a statistical average or mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methodologies for the displayed final rating have evolved over the past decades. It has seen major changes with Bayesian averages being a standard for a while when it was leveraged to calculate and weigh reviews for the final rating on a variety of platforms (especially when only a few reviews were available).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayesian averages are highly dependent on the data size/population and it involves using the previous mean combined with a pre-existing belief in the form of a constant, &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;. This constant is the number of observations from past data sets and is a core aspect of Bayesian interpretation. As the data size changes, &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;, also fluctuates, and it can affect the final rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, we see a rise of bespoke black-box systems that are dictated by machine learned models which factor various variables of a review to contribute to the average rating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=GQUXAMY73JFRVJHE&quot;&gt;(read here how Amazon explains it)&lt;/a&gt;. It is difficult to say if Bayesian averages are part of the final calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt;Fake and Unreliable reviews&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the flour is spoiled, what quality of bread will it produce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the star rating average is unreliable if the data constituting it is contaminated with fake or unreliable reviews. As reviews power a rapidly growing digital economy, in tandem, fraud flourishes. The amount of trustworthy opinions has severely deteriorated since the turn of the decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, there was an average of &lt;strong&gt;30% of fake reviews&lt;/strong&gt; on popular eCommerce platforms and, by 2020, that number has skyrocketed to new highs we have never witnessed before. Fraudsters exploited the global lockdown situation by gamifying the review systems across the Internet to make a buck &lt;a href=&quot;https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1&quot;&gt;(read more about it here)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, unfortunately, renders the star rating system completely useless in the face of a flood of fraud regardless of the fact if a true mean is calculated or a bespoke ML model is utilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, consumers have a couple of options to combat these flaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researching a product across a variety of sources and looking up video reviews where the owner of the product you’re interested in is actually show-casing it (thus proving ownership) is highly recommended, especially when the product is a high priced item. If you can only find one source for ratings + reviews, make sure the store has a good return policy in case your experience with the product does not match up to the reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, use an automated AI powered solution such as ours, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fakespot.com&quot;&gt;Fakespot&lt;/a&gt;, that makes reviews and, those stars, more trustworthy. Fakespot reports provide an Adjusted Rating that weighs reviews based off authenticity and then recalculates it with trust being the primary factor of the final adjusted rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot for free today and stop wondering if those reviews are real or not. Download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/fakespot-fake-reviews-amazon/&quot;&gt;Firefox extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;Fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">There is one indisputable and ubiquitous feature of eCommerce platforms that powers a huge chunk of sales and conversions. That is the ratings (or reviews) system.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One week update after app takedown</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/23/one-week-update-after-app-takedown" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One week update after app takedown" /><published>2021-07-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/23/one-week-update-after-app-takedown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/23/one-week-update-after-app-takedown">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a week since the Fakespot iOS app was taken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what we have learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazon, a 1.84 trillion dollar company (!!), launched a coordinated PR attack to spread lies and disinformation about Fakespot (we have raised around $7mm).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our internal data shows us that users were increasingly choosing the Fakespot app over Amazon’s own app to shop on their own platform (!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazon has bought out keywords for “Fakespot” on the App Store and other places to control what people see. Unlimited resources at work to destroy our company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have Black Friday level traffic on our website and record level downloads (thanks Amazon!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This just confirms that consumers do not trust Amazon and want Fakespot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Amazon doesn’t realize is that Fakespot is part of a powerful movement, a movement that is for the consumer and for the people. Their actions have confirmed (buying keywords on our name and spreading lies to the media) that deception is the only key strategy that works for Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Founder and CEO of Fakespot, I am incredibly proud and privileged to be leading a company that can accomplish such things. We are a platform that is for the consumer and people. Amazon’s actions only validate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t end here, stay tuned my fellow Fakespotters and friends. We have a lot of exciting developments to announce in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been a week since the Fakespot iOS app was taken down.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dear Jeff,</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/19/dear-jeff" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dear Jeff," /><published>2021-07-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/19/dear-jeff</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/19/dear-jeff">&lt;p&gt;As you embark on your trip into space, you leave behind a company that claims to be the most customer-obsessed company on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear to us today that Amazon has lost its touch with reality, fighting and crushing smaller businesses like Fakespot, that actually help consumers fight fake reviews and scams on Amazon. We empower consumers with data to make more informed decisions about their purchase decisions, but apparently Amazon does not care about consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions to remove Fakespot from the App Store prove that Amazon is not a customer-obsessed company. Instead, Amazon is profit-obsessed and will do anything to hide the truth from its customers. Consumers and the people deserve much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon has grown so much and so fast that the amount of fraud on the platform exploded in lockstep. You lead a brainwashing marketing campaign to convince us all that Amazon is the best thing for consumers because of low prices and easy returns. The prices on Amazon aren’t even the best anymore. Consumers have become so dependent on Amazon because we pay for Prime every year, even when the cost goes up, and that initial Prime investment causes us to think twice about going to a competitor because we already paid for shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff, this great power you wield demands great responsibility. You have not done enough to protect us from brands and sellers who lie, cheat and deceive. You make your own rules and ignore the law to do whatever you want, to whomever you want, including your own corporate and warehouse employees. This is not what an ethical, responsible, and inclusive technology company should be doing, but there is more to the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all think we are only buying products from Amazon, but at the end of day, we are the actual product. Amazon knows more about their customers than any other company. But armed with a monstrous corporate PR machine you get away with it and you’re only considered an eCommerce marketplace with a giant smile for a face. Amazon, through its fly-wheel, has enough data to know who our partners are, what medical conditions we have, what income bracket we’re in, and on and on. You have a treasure trove of data about all of us. This is what I would call the greatest heist of the 21st century. It was achieved by duping all of us into thinking that Amazon is actually a net-positive creation for society and something that we actually needed in our lives. The enlightenment is here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I checked on customer-centricity, it did not involve knowing who our partners are and what ailments we have. When did you lose sight of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot and the apps we build, protect consumers from all of these problems and bring radical transparency to the Amazon platform. You may not realize it, but Fakespot was actually started after I was ripped off on Amazon after seeing that you were doing nothing about it. Now we are in 2021 and the problem has only grown exponentially. Fakespot has been innovating and growing to solve the problems of fake reviews, deceptive sellers and eCommerce fraud because you have failed to protect your own consumers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a shame that Amazon considers Fakespot a threat. We are a small 20-person team based in New York City that is supremely passionate about bringing back trust to the Internet and eradicating the problems you’ve failed so hard at fixing. While we are working on solving the problem of disinformation on the Internet, your team is working hard to destroy us. The reasons Amazon has listed for the takedown notice to Apple for our iOS app are deceptive, misleading and untruthful, just like the many reviews on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you enter space while looking back on Earth, I hope you ask yourself the question: Which side am I on? The consumer or my never-ending wallet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saoud&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">As you embark on your trip into space, you leave behind a company that claims to be the most customer-obsessed company on Earth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Information Asymmetry platforms</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/06/the-information-asymmetry-platforms" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Information Asymmetry platforms" /><published>2021-07-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/06/the-information-asymmetry-platforms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/07/06/the-information-asymmetry-platforms">&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite pastimes is etymology, the study of the origin of words, that usually leads me to a Latin and historical rabbit-hole that I enjoy. &lt;em&gt;Caveat emptor&lt;/em&gt; is a phrase you’ve probably heard or read before. Latin for &lt;strong&gt;“Let the buyer beware/be wary”&lt;/strong&gt;, an Ancient Roman concept and maxim that is part of modern law and economic contract principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, the phrase puts forward that the responsibility is on the buyer for the due diligence on the product that they will be purchasing from a seller. The buyer has to ascertain and be satisfied the product fits the seller’s description. It is fascinating to see that humans and their interactions haven’t really changed much since the early days of civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we analyze the phrase further, it can be said that the seller has more information about the product or service than you, the buyer. As such, the buyer has to counteract this lack of information by conducting research, vetting and verification. This imbalance of information between the buyer and seller is part of a subject in economics, security and contract theory named &lt;strong&gt;Information Asymmetry&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Asymmetry&lt;/strong&gt; is a broad concept that can be applied beyond the domain of buyer and seller transactions, including markets, game theory, governance, diplomacy and much more. We will focus on the classic buyer and seller transaction in the digital realm showing how information asymmetry affects you today, &lt;em&gt;perhaps even without you knowing it!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Ubers, Grubhubs and Amazons of the world provide us with services and products that we are increasingly dependent on, in our modern, digitally intertwined lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think back 10 years to see how you were using the Internet compared with today, you will come to a realization that you are buying more online and relying on apps/services more than ever before:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many of us pay for &lt;em&gt;one or more subscriptions&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many of us &lt;em&gt;shop on Amazon&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many of us had a &lt;em&gt;telemedicine call&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these questions holds an element of information asymmetry that has been shaped by the platform that hosted the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, information asymmetry can be visualized as a balance. Below is a diagram when the state of &lt;strong&gt;perfect information&lt;/strong&gt; is achieved, where the seller and buyer have equal amounts of information between them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/perfect_information.png&quot; alt=&quot;Perfect_Information&quot; style=&quot;width: 950px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of perfect information between a seller and buyer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for consumers today, the information asymmetry in a digital transaction usually looks like this &lt;strong&gt;and it continues to trend downwards for the buyer&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/imperfect_information.png&quot; alt=&quot;Imperfect_Information&quot; style=&quot;width: 900px; margin-left: 5px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of imperfect information, the seller has the advantege over the buyer.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the diagram above and end up asking yourself the questions &lt;strong&gt;“Why is that?”&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;“How is that even possible?”&lt;/strong&gt;, you have already self-admitted to having less information than the seller in the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this, let’s examine how we interact with Amazon, the largest eCommerce platform on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By signing up on Amazon, and buying on the platform, we have already provided Amazon a wealth of data about ourselves. What categories of products we tend to buy, what brands we favor, how big our family is, what is our income bracket, what medical conditions do we have and so on. At this point, you are at a disadvantage, information wise, and the platform that hosts you knows more about you than you do, about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say we are ready to buy something on Amazon, and as a consumer, you trust all the information you see on a product listing Amazon. After all, Amazon’s logo is a big yellow smile, how can you not trust the information on the website. Here again is another huge disadvantage. Armed with the knowledge that over &lt;strong&gt;40% of reviews of Amazon are fake&lt;/strong&gt;, the chances of getting a &lt;strong&gt;used or counterfeit product is increasing&lt;/strong&gt;, and that you may buy a product from a 3rd party seller that may use your information for &lt;strong&gt;nefarious purposes&lt;/strong&gt; (such as solicitation and marketing), the symmetry of information can be clearly drawn. You as a buyer are stuck in a &lt;em&gt;flywheel of misinformation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is most interesting about the information asymmetry case on Amazon is how historically the balance of information between you (&lt;em&gt;the buyer&lt;/em&gt;) and Amazon (&lt;em&gt;the seller&lt;/em&gt;) has been dramatically changing. The lowering of the balance of information on the buyer’s side is evident, as Amazon got better in analyzing personal information and millions of third party sellers dominate the platform. It is not hard to see that &lt;strong&gt;information asymmetry is a critical component&lt;/strong&gt; of the business model that these platforms operate with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have used Amazon (or other equally sized behemoths) for the last 20 years, you can confidently see how skewed the information asymmetry balance is in favor of the platform versus the consumer. That’s how &lt;strong&gt;monopolies of knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; are formed, but that is a topic for another blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information asymmetry is a concept that I have found myself always reminded of when we’re developing and building products at Fakespot&lt;/strong&gt;. At our core, the products that Fakespot provides to users revolves around research, vetting and verification of information to increase the balance in favor of the consumer versus the platforms. We are proud to be building a company that actually brings back the balance to the consumer as this was one of the reasons that brought Fakespot into existence, my disappointment in getting scammed on Amazon many years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When was the last time information asymmetry affected you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot today and become a more informed consumer when shopping online, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/fakespot-fake-reviews-amazon/&quot;&gt;Firefox extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">One of my favorite pastimes is etymology, the study of the origin of words, that usually leads me to a Latin and historical rabbit-hole that I enjoy. Caveat emptor is a phrase you’ve probably heard or read before. Latin for “Let the buyer beware/be wary”, an Ancient Roman concept and maxim that is part of modern law and economic contract principles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amazon Fake Review Data Breach</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/amazon-fake-review-data-breach" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon Fake Review Data Breach" /><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/the-amazon-fake-review-data-breach</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/05/10/amazon-fake-review-data-breach">&lt;p&gt;The recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safetydetectives.com/blog/amazon-reviews-leak-report/&quot;&gt;data leak report&lt;/a&gt; exposing millions of records incriminating professional reviewers and sellers engaging in fake review fraud did not surprise us at all at Fakespot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen Facebook groups, WhatsApp groups, WeChat and many other social platforms hosting the meeting grounds for unscrupulous sellers/agencies/brands to get in touch with folks that would write reviews for their products, obviously in exchange for compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first detected the first signs of these types of promotional reviews in the tail end of 2015 and they exploded in volume by 2016 and 2017. The incentivized reviews had disclaimers that mentioned the review authors received products for free/compensation in exchange for writing the review. The amount of these types of compensated reviews reached epidemic levels and Amazon had to react. Amazon officially banned any reviews with text mentioning that kind of disclaimer in the late months of 2016 by doing specific keyword scanning within submitted reviews. The ripple effect of this ban is clearly seen today with social media platforms ending up hosting the subterfuge of Amazon sellers to obtain fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/compensated_review.png&quot; alt=&quot;An example of a compensated review from 2017 for a book&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An example of a compensated review from 2017 for a book&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the companies in the data leak was a relatively well known brand that is a competitor to Anker, RAVPower and other brands in the electronic accessories space, a hotbed of fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular brand named Aukey was implicated in the data leak and had hundreds of listings taken down by Amazon. As of today, there were 292 listings on Amazon down 77% from 1,236 listings that Fakespot has analyzed with over close to half a million reviews &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com/company/aukey&quot;&gt;(https://www.fakespot.com/company/aukey)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/auk.png&quot; alt=&quot;AUKEY Fakespot Company Page Screenshot&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;AUKEY Fakespot Company Page Screenshot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the average Fakespot grade and adjusted rating for the company’s products, the results aren’t flattering. We can say that it wasn’t a shock to see this brand (and others) be included in the data dump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subset  of Fakespot’s models have been trained specifically to pick up on signals that reviews and reviewers can be sourced via these promotional review campaigns. We believe these types of reviews are the more insidious fake reviews as they are mostly written by humans that have an intrinsic bias embedded. Fakespot’s engines look for a targeted amount of historic and present parameters to determine if the reviews belong to such a category and are pointed out to our users via our Fakespot grade or our reports with the deception level metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will this data leak change anything for the current trend of fake reviews on Amazon?&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t think so. A lot of the banned sellers will be reinstated and probably a good amount of the reviews will be part of the Amazon “purges” (read my &lt;a href=&quot;https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; to understand these events) but it is a slap on the wrist and the fake review economy continues full steam ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what happens when you have millions of 3rd party sellers running amok on the Amazon platform and so much profit to be gained by duping unsuspecting consumers with these types of reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot today and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real or not, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">The recent data leak report exposing millions of records incriminating professional reviewers and sellers engaging in fake review fraud did not surprise us at all at Fakespot.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is buying your influence in 2021?</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is buying your influence in 2021?" /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2021/01/04/who-is-buying-your-influence-in-2021">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What can money buy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on who you are asking, the answers vary:&lt;br /&gt;
Power, comfort, land .. maybe even a sprinkle of Fake News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How about your influence? Is that for sale?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the explosive rise of TikTok, it was only a matter of time until we started seeing videos such as the ones in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/the-goods/2020/12/15/22174581/walmart-amazon-tiktok-employee-worker-influencer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;this article by Vox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employees in the monster factory warehouses of Amazon are now using the social platform as a medium to showcase the dark side of getting your shipment in 2 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of constant surveillance, optimized algorithmic performance evaluations, and being a human robot are hallmarks of the job. More and more videos trickle onto social media uncovering the reality of modern commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the table, this must look like an onslaught of nightmare PR and press. How do you fight this fire that only seems to be growing and growing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would depend on the size of your treasury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a treasury the size of several countries cumulative GDP, you might as well fight fire with fire, change peoples’ perceptions and distort reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Vine&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pay to get 5 star reviews with Amazon Vine program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/amazon-influencer-how-to-make-money-2019-2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Influencer program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/whats-an-amazon-fc-ambassador-and-are-they-okay-1837274685&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Influencer army&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/news/tiktok-sale-deadline-elapses-as-negotiations-with-us-continue/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart is seeking to increase their stake in TikTok&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An army of influencers fighting under the banner of the wronged and the oppressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait.. which side is the wronged one again? The Influencer Amnesia has struck, yet again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a feedback loop running right in-front of us. The influencers posting rave tweets and posts are also the ones that are buying fake followers, upvotes and many more. The savage cycle only repeats itself and proliferates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like the industry is too far gone to revert. What is even more astounding is that buying influencers doesn’t just limit itself to PR and media. Every facet of the Internet is affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influencers aren’t only working to improve companies’ reputations by tweeting or using TikTok. By now, it should come as no surprise that &lt;a href=&quot;https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;more than 40%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (!) of the reviews you’re reading may have been manipulated and are unreliable. These types of campaigns are only growing with more reviews being written with the only intent to influence you and your buying decision. Without you even knowing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try Fakespot today and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real or not, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">What can money buy?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Let’s talk about fake reviews - part 1</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let's talk about fake reviews - part 1" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/10/19/lets-talk-about-fake-reviews-part-1">&lt;p&gt;Fake reviews garner much attention and controversy worldwide. It is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; primary reason Fakespot was created. Fakespot was launched after I was scammed on Amazon with a product that had hundreds of fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading the reviews for this product, it was obvious that the seller had implanted fake reviews with the use of bots, spiced up with some human input. The product was freshly launched and it had &lt;em&gt;hundreds of 5 star reviews&lt;/em&gt; in a matter of hours for a completely no name brand!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already familiar with black hat techniques fraudsters use to increase their listings’ rankings due to my security background, a passion I developed in my early teenage years. In case you were wondering… Yes, I was a hacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the age of 18, I submitted my first bug bounties to the Zero Day Initiative, a pioneer of the bug bounty programs when there were none. The first vulnerability I discovered was a &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft PowerPoint&lt;/strong&gt; buffer overflow. My research later lead me to finding bugs in software ranging from &lt;strong&gt;Adobe PDF Reader&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;WinAmp&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Foxit&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;VLC Player&lt;/strong&gt; to some more &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;check out my publicly published vulnerabilities/exploits &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exploit-db.com/search?e_author=skd&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re curious&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/metasploit_pp_exploit.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Metasploit module for the PowerPoint vulnerability I found way back in the day.&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black; max-width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Metasploit module for the PowerPoint vulnerability I found way back in the day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funny story: I applied for a Microsoft internship at the time I received the payout for the bug bounty. Back in those days, Microsoft was notorious for “hating” on anyone who would find weaknesses in their products especially security researchers. Needless to say, they immediately rejected my application. It just shows how much Microsoft has changed since then.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My love for security has taught me that, reverse engineering to the lowest level is always critical. Especially, if you want to understand the fundamentals and scope to the problem you are encountering. That mindset helped me discover a completely different class of vulnerabilities altogether, the social context vulnerabilities in eCommerce: &lt;strong&gt;fake reviews&lt;/strong&gt; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot was initially built to automate the process of analyzing the trustworthiness of reviews. After all, who has hours of free time to dissect and verify the reviews they’re reading? Since the launch of Fakespot in 2015, the state of fake reviews and eCommerce fraud has emerged and evolved in ways that I wouldn’t have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving in to fake reviews and eCommerce fraud, let’s talk about eCommerce and take a look at the total volume and growth of sales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shopify_sales_graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;eCommerce past years growth and forecast for 2021 - Source: Shopify&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;eCommerce past years growth and forecast for 2021 - Source: Shopify&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;eCommerce sales are forecast to be close to &lt;em&gt;$4 trillion dollars&lt;/em&gt; this year. That is &lt;em&gt;nearly 20%&lt;/em&gt; of the GDP for the United States in 2019 alone. These numbers are astonishing and showcase the vast opportunities in eCommerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more sales happen online in the year of 2020. We can only see eCommerce gobbling up even more sales from brick and mortal retail as consumers work from home in quarantine. This is indeed the era of the &lt;em&gt;digital gold rush&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Make no mistake, it also the era of the digital Wild West.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/wild_west_meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;That's the truth, Clint.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;That’s the truth, Clint.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive into trends we see with fake reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot has analyzed over &lt;strong&gt;8 billion reviews&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;1 billion reviewers&lt;/strong&gt; and served over &lt;strong&gt;20 million users&lt;/strong&gt; visiting &lt;strong&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/strong&gt;. From our analysis, we can clearly understand the trends that show the increase in fraud over the last 3 years with each month in comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/fakespot_avg_graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;The monthly average of analyses that had &amp;gt;= 30% unreliable reviews - Source: Fakespot&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The monthly average of analyses that had &amp;gt;= 30% unreliable reviews - Source: Fakespot&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data unveils the whole story for the trend of fake reviews. We have comparable rises each year in the amount of unreliable reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the averages from March 2020 to August 2020 reached &lt;strong&gt;record numbers never seen before&lt;/strong&gt;. This sequence of increases would only occur in Black Friday and Christmas shopping seasons of prior years. Sellers are quoted as saying “It was Black Friday everyday” &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/article/people-shopping-more-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and we all experienced the widespread stock depletion on Amazon and other platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also take note that in September 2020 Amazon significantly &lt;strong&gt;purged&lt;/strong&gt;, albeit in a delayed fashion, a large chunk of fake reviews to move it down from the &lt;strong&gt;43.75%&lt;/strong&gt; average we see in August. Likely, in preparation for Prime Day and the impending holiday shopping season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is quite different, &lt;em&gt;to say the least&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the majority of the world went into lockdown the importance of reviews increases for sellers and consumers alike. We shop online, unable to judge the product by touching, feeling and physically testing it. Thus, we heavily rely on the opinions of others that have purchased the product. &lt;strong&gt;I believe one of the great innovations of the Internet is shared knowledge, and reviews are a conduit of that.&lt;/strong&gt; Unfortunately, sellers also know that reviews can make or break their sales and they are abusing that to the maximum for their advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This overview of the general trends is useful in understanding the scale of eCommerce fraud. Fake reviews and the fraud surrounding eCommerce is extensive, complex and deep. To go through all the topics requires a sequence of posts with this being the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to try out Fakespot and spend less time reading and wondering if the reviews are real, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; or visit us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fakespot.com&quot;&gt;fakespot.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Fake reviews garner much attention and controversy worldwide. It is the primary reason Fakespot was created. Fakespot was launched after I was scammed on Amazon with a product that had hundreds of fake reviews. When reading the reviews for this product, it was obvious that the seller had implanted fake reviews with the use of bots, spiced up with some human input. The product was freshly launched and it had hundreds of 5 star reviews in a matter of hours for a completely no name brand!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fakespot Highlights - AI powered summaries</title><link href="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fakespot Highlights - AI powered summaries" /><published>2020-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://saoudkhalifah.com/2020/09/29/fakespot-highlights-ai-powered-summaries">&lt;p&gt;Super excited to announce that we’ve just released, &lt;strong&gt;Fakespot Highlights&lt;/strong&gt;, a powerful AI generated addition to our analysis reports on Fakespot.com that consists of direct summaries of reviews that you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to know about before purchasing a product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/fakespot_highlights.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Fakespot Highlights&quot; style=&quot;border: 2px solid black;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fakespot Highlights will organize relevant information into 5 categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;What is the product’s quality and characteristics?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packaging/appearance&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How is the product’s packaging and physical attributes?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitiveness&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How does the product stack up to the competition?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shipping&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;What was the general experience with the product’s shipping?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;How was/is the price?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlights will also further categorize the details by sentiment with Positive, Neutral and Negative sentiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new feature is powered by multiple machine learned models, both supervised and unsupervised, built by our talented data science team. The models were trained on over 7 billion+ reviews using our proprietary in-house stack that delivers blazing fast results in an eCommerce setting. That means no 3rd party APIs and no reliance on outside solutions (always awesome in my book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try Fakespot Highlights, download our &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/fakespot-analyze-fake-ama/nakplnnackehceedgkgkokbgbmfghain&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;. After installing the extension, browse to a product page on Amazon.com and click to Analyze or Reanalyze. I would also recommend analyzing a product you’ve owned for a while and see if the Highlights match your personal experience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are always excited to build products and features that help our users in getting the best eCommerce experience. This feature is currently in Beta but we are constantly improving the technology in an evolutionary manner. If you have any suggestions, do not hesitate to get in &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:saoud@fakespot.com&quot;&gt;touch with me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saoud Khalifah</name></author><summary type="html">Super excited to announce that we’ve just released, Fakespot Highlights, a powerful AI generated addition to our analysis reports on Fakespot.com that consists of direct summaries of reviews that you have to know about before purchasing a product.</summary></entry></feed>